Guide to the Edwin Martin Photograph Collection 1994-2001 PR 96
New-York Historical Society
Edwin Martin Photograph Collection
1994-2001
New-York Historical Society
PR 96
0.9 Linear feet (1 box)
The photographs in this collection document stores, store fronts, street vendors, and various tradesmen such as butchers, bakers, and barbers in New York City, mostly in Manhattan.
Provenance
Gift of Edwin Martin, 2000 and 2001.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to thirty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Biographical Note
Edwin Martin was born in 1943, and educated at Florida State University, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and Indiana University. He worked as a news photographer in the mid-1980s, and served as the photo editor for the Newark Star-Ledger from 1999-2000. During the late 1990s, Martin taught in the Department of Journalism and Mass Media at Rutgers University. In addition, Martin was Curator of Photography at the North Carolina State University Visual Arts Center from 1990-1993.
Martin's photographic projects include "Postergirls," photos of public posters, "The Readers," photographs concerning the nature and activity of reading, and "Mud Show," which documents traveling circus shows. His proximity to New York City in the 1990s allowed him to focus on two different portfolios of photographs: "NYNY," and "NY Metier," which both highlight street vendors, storefronts, and street life.
Scope and Content Note
The Edwin Martin Photograph Collection spans the period from 1994-2001 and contains images from the photographer's portfolios, "NYNY," and "NY Metier." The collection is divided into two series, after the portfolio titles. Photographs document New York City stores, storefronts, street vendors, and various tradesmen such as bakers, butchers, and barbers.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into two series, "NYNY" and "NY Metier."
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Other photographs of street vendors, working people, and storefronts can be found in the Irving Browning Photograph Collection (PR 009) and throughout the Photographer File (PR 050).
Street vendors -- New York (State) -- New York.; Storefronts -- New York (State) -- New York.; Stores, Retail -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Gelatin silver prints.
- Series I: "NYNY"
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I includes 61 11x14 silver gelatin prints from the portfolio of the same title. Photographs are arranged alphabetically after the photographer's title. Views show storefronts throughout the city, from Bergdorf Goodman to the Fulton Fish Market.
  Photographs are arranged alphabetically according to the photographer's title. General locations of photographs are in brackets.
  - Art Supplies [Elizabeth St.], 1997 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bananas [Seventh Ave.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bananas [Seventh Ave.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bergdorf Goodman [Fifth Ave.], 1995 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Big Sale [Sixth Ave.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Birthday Suit [W. 4th St.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Blowup Animals [West Broadway], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bodega [Third Ave.], 1994 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bodega and Bike [MacDougal St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Body Piercing [W. 8th St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bones [Amsterdam Ave.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bounty [Ninth Ave., 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Canal Surplus, 1997 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Candy Vendor [Seventh Ave.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Carl & Sons [Orchard St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Change [Times Square], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chapel [Elizabeth St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cigar Company [Mulberry St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cigar Store Indians [Beekman St.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cigar Store Window [Fifth Ave.], 1997 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Deceit! Hot Dogs [72nd St.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Esposito's Meat Shop [Ninth Ave.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Flower Vendor [Grand Central Station], 1997 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fox Sewing Machines [38th St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fruit [Court St., Brooklyn], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Fruit [W. 23rd and Eighth Ave.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fruit and Vegetables [Mott St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Fruit on Canal, 1997 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gourmet [Seventh Ave.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gyros [Seventh Ave.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hats [Lexington Ave.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hijacked Gods, 1997 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Horse and Wheel [Lafayette St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Horse Ride [Ninth Ave.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Italian Ice [Orchard St. and Houston St.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Jewelry at NYPL [42nd St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Junk on Houston, 1997 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - L&K Clothing [Catherine St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Magazines [Bleecker St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - New York Chair [Bowery], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Nice and Spicey [Ninth Ave.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Palm Reading [Eldridge St.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Peacock Feathers [Union Square], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Plumbing [Third Ave.] (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Portraits [Fulton St.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Psychic [Fifth Ave.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Sales Help [Fish's Eddy, Broadway], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Sandwich Shop [Amsterdam Ave.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Square Meal [Broadway], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - St. Gandolfo [Mulberry St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Street Cobbler [Grand St.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Thompson Street News, 1997 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Tip of the Hat [Lexington Ave.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Vegetable Vendor [Canal St.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Vendor Facing the Light [Broadway, 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Village Sax [Carmine St.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Wedding Flowers [City Hall], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Wigs [Prince St., 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Wigs in Stock [Christopher St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Windows at Saks, 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - World Champions [Church St.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Zito [Bleecker St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II: "NY Metier"
  Series II includes 46 11x14 silver gelatin prints from the portfolio of the same title. Photographs are arranged alphabetically after the photographer's title. Several of these photographs show Zito's Bakery, on Bleecker Street, which closed in 2004.
  - Albanese [Mott St.], 2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Atlas Meats [Washington St.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Atlas Meats [Washington St.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Baker and Loaves [Zito's, Bleecker St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Baker at Oven [Zito's, Bleecker St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bakery Workbench [Zito's, Bleecker St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Barber [Mott St.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bernard Faerman [Faerman Cash Register], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bodega and Clerk [Seventh Ave.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bows and Bridges [Gage, Walker St.], 2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bread in the Window [Zito's, Bleecker St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bringing up Bread [Zito's, Bleecker St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Butcher and Cow [Tenth Ave.], 1997 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Butcher Sharpening [Pino's, MacDougal St.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Buttons and Ribbons [Liechtenstein, Delancey St.], 2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cappuccino & Tattoo [St. Marks Place], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Chuen Lee fabrics [Division St.], 2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cigar Company [Mulberry St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cigars [Quisequeyana Cigars, Church St.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cigars [Quisequeyana Cigars, Church St.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - Doctor Plays [Rick Rajca, Village Flute and Sax, Carmine St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - Faerman Cash Register [Bowery], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - Faerman's Work Bench [Bowery], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - Fox Sewing Machines [38th St.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - French Culinary Institute [Grand St.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - Icing [D'Aiuto, Eighth Ave.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - Joe Fox [Fox Sewing Machines, 38th St.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - Liechtenstein's [Delancey St.], 2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - Mannequins [22nd St.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - Mark's [Bowery, 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - Meat Packer [Washington St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - Murray's Cheese Shop [Bleecker St.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - Peretti Seafood [South St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - Pork [Grand St.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - Pots and Pans [Bowery], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
  - Quisequeyana Cigars [Church St.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
  - Segal Fabric Center [Orchard St.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
  - String Repair [Gage, Walker St.], 2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
  - String Repair at Stairs[Gage, Walker St.], 2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 21)
  - Tattooist [St. Marks Place], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
  - Three Bakers [Parisi], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
  - Two Bakers [Zito's, Bleecker St.], 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
  - Village Sax [Carmine St.], 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
  - York Barber Shop [Lexington Ave.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 22)
  - Zelig Blumenthal [Scribe of Jerusalem, Essex St.], 2000 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)
  - Zelig Blumenthal [Scribe of Jerusalem, Essex St.], 2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 23)